(gentle music)
We are in The Harvard Plate Stacks.
So this is the top floor of three floors
that holds over 600,000 glass plate negatives
of the night sky.
The collection did not start to what we know today
until the bequest given to us by Anna Palmer Draper.
She and Henry Draper, her husband, had their own observatory
in Hastings-on-Hudson,
and they were both interested in spectra.
So if you take the light from a star,
you have it go through a prism and hit a glass plate,
that'll capture a spectra.
It'll look black and white in our collection,
but it's in a rainbow color.
And they were trying to figure out
what the stars were made out of.
We knew here on Earth
that each element has its own unique signature.
So we can use that by comparing spectra
of known elements here on earth with spectras of the stars
to figure out what unique elements are inside of each star.
So there was a conference in New York City,
specifically gathering the greatest minds
of astronomy across America.
And our director at the time, Edward Pickering, went.
And unfortunately, Mr. Draper actually caught ill,
and five days later, after this big gathering,
he passed away.
And Anna, she wanted to continue their scientific legacy
after his death,
but realized that she couldn't devote
the same amount of time that she used to
in order to actually get the work
that she and Henry were hoping to get done.
But luckily, Edward Pickering was able to convince her
that Harvard could continue on with this legacy.
That then created "The Henry Draper Memorial" catalog,
and one of the central parts of our collection today,
where 1/3 of the 600,000 glass plate negatives
are actually these particular plates
that are taking different stars
and letting us see what they are made out of
by taking their light and casting it into a spectra.
One of these women who would become central
in "The Henry Draper Catalogue" was Annie Jump Cannon.
Annie was lucky enough to go to Wellesley,
one of the earliest women's schools in America,
and study at a brand-new observatory there.
In 1896, she actually started volunteering here
at the Harvard College Observatory.
Annie was tasked with going through not hundreds,
but hundreds of thousands of stars
and to put them into stellar classifications.
So she's looking at the spectra plates,
and she saw this pattern,
and that ended up giving us
the Harvard stellar standard sequence,
or the Harvard sequence, OBAFGKM, that we still use today
to let us know from a star spectrum,
what kind of star is it, what elements is it made out of,
and how along its evolution will it go.
So on one plate, she has hundreds,
if not thousands, of stars,
each with its own spectra cast onto the glass.
And inside of that spectra with magnification,
Annie could see the absorption and emission lines
that would let her, just by sight,
be able to realize which one
of the stellar classifications she would assign to them.
Over her lifetime, she would actually classify
over 200,000 stars.
She had this amazing knack that never was surpassed
in our history and was able to just,
with that little blip of spectra,
be able to know which category these stars fell into.
"The Henry Draper Catalogue," which is still used today,
is pivotal in science.
Annie would actually publish nine volumes
that would be these tables of a HD number,
Henry Draper number, that would tell you what star it is,
and then it would give you a classification letter
for each one of these.
And now with these classifications, not only were we able
to start parsing out what stars are made out of,
but also, the ways that our universe is evolving.
(gentle music)
(gentle music continues)